Women's Clubs Collection, 1812-1995
Sophia Smith Collection, Smith College
Women's clubs collection
1812-1995
MS 485
1 box, 2 volumes (.75 linear ft.)
Sophia Smith Collection Smith College Northampton, MA
Collection of files on women's clubs in the United States, primarily in New England.
This is a collection of small files on various women's clubs in the United States, primarily in New England. The collection dates from 1812 to the present and includes charitable, literary, political, social and religious clubs. Some of those represented are the Concord Female Charitable Society (1812-1912), Mother's Study Club (Cambridge), the Home Study Club (Ashland, Mass.), Woman's National Democratic Club (Washington, DC), Worcester Woman's Club, and the Woman's Baptist Social Union (Boston). There is also a small amount of material on African American club women Josephine St. Pierre Ruffin (Women's ERA Club of Boston) and Julia Davis (Saint Louis City Association of Colored Women's Clubs). Types of materials include programs, yearbooks, calendars, by-laws, fliers, newsletters, histories, articles, books, pamphlets, and other published materials. There are also books, articles and pamphlets on the history of women's club movement, individual clubs and clubwomen. These include The Mother of Clubs: Caroline M. Seymour Severance, ed. Ella Giles Ruddy; and Reminiscences of the Springfield Women's Club, 1884-1924, by Carrie Niles Whitcomb.
Information on Use
Terms of Access and Use
The collection is open to research according to the regulations of the Sophia Smith Collection.
Additions to the Collection
Periodic additions to collection are expected and may not be reflected in this record.
History of the Collection
Items in this collection were either purchased or given to the Sophia Smith Collection by various donors. New materials are acquired and added to the collection from time to time.
Search Terms
Women--Societies and clubs--United States--History--Sources; Clubs--United States--History--Sources; Women--New England--History--Sources; Sophia Smith Collection
Contents List
  - Contents (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - The Afternoon Club, Gardner, Mass.: publications, 1906-07, 1910-11 (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - American Women's Clubs: articles, pamphlet, 1899-1975 (Box 1)
  - Birdwoman Club: photograph, undated (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - The Cabot Club, Middleboro, Mass.: Calendar, 1909-10 (Box 1)
  - Chautauqua-by-the-Sea for Eastern New England, 30th Annual Session: publications, 1910 (Box 1)
  - Concord Female Charitable Society: publications, 1812-1912 (Box 1)
  - The Cosmopolitan Club, Springfield, Mass (?): publications, 1910-12 (Box 1)
  - District of Columbia Federation of Women's Clubs, Washington, D.C.: Yearbook, 1902 (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - Dover Women's Club, Dover, N.H.: publications, 1905-06 (Box 1)
  - Edgewood Women's Club, Providence, R.I.: Yearbook, 1907-08 (Box 1)
  - Enfield, The Woman's Club of, Enfield, Conn.: Calendar, 1900-01 (Box 1)
  - Fortnightly Club, Bath, Maine: Yearbook, 1909-10 (Box 1)
  - Friends in Council, Turners Falls, Mass.: publications, 1904-05 (Box 1)
  - The Froebel Society, Brooklyn, N.Y.: Souvenir, 1898; Program, 1901-02, 1904-05 (Box 1)
  - General Federation of Women's Clubs: clippings, pamphlets, and articles, 1889-1957 (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - H.H. Club, Dayton, Ohio: publications, 1893-94, 1898-99 (Box 1, Folder 6)
  - Hackensack, New Jersey, Women's Club of: Year Book, 1912-13 (Box 1)
  - Home Study Club, Ashland, Mass.: publications, 1908-09 (Box 1)
  - Hyde Park Current Events Club, Boston, Mass.: publications, 1907-08 (Box 1)
  - Kosmos Club, Wakefield, Mass.: Yearbook, 1905-06 (Box 1)
  - The Medford Women's Club, Medford, Mass.: publications, 1899-1900 (Box 1, Folder 7)
  - Middlesex Women's Club, Lowell, Mass.: Year Book, 1898-1900 (Box 1)
  - Milford Woman's Club, Milford, (State?): publications, 1905-06 (Box 1)
  - Mother's Study Club, Cambridge, Mass.: publications, 1964 (Box 1)
  - National Association of Negro Business & Professional Women's Clubs, Inc.: report, 1949-50 (Box 1, Folder 8)
  - New Britain, Conn., Women's Club of: publications, 1905-06 (Box 1)
  - New England Women's Club, Boston, Mass.: publications, 1899 (Box 1)
  - New Hampshire Missionary Society, Female Club Institution: annual report, 1830-33 (Box 1)
  - Ohio State Association of Colored Women's Clubs: newsletter, undated (Box 1)
  - Old and New, Malden, Mass.: publications, 1898-99, 1907-08 (Box 1)
  - Oneonta, New York, The Woman's Club of: Yearbook, 1899-00 (Box 1)
  - Quota Club: article, 1927 (Box 1)
  - Rhode Island Women's Club, Providence, R.I.: Year Book, 1906 (Box 1)
  - St. Johnsbury Women's Club, St. Johnsbury, Vermont: Year Book, 1909/1910 (Box 1, Folder 9)
  - The Saint Louis City Association of Colored Women's Clubs, Inc. (Julia Davis): correspondence, pamphlets, and articles, 1961-64 (Box 1)
  - Sarah F. Doyle Club, Providence, R.I.: Year Book, 1906/1907, 1910/1911 (Box 1)
  - Southern Federation of Colored Women's Clubs: program, 1902 (Box 1)
  - Springfield, Ohio, Woman's Club of: publications, 1902/1903, 1912/1913 (Box 1)
  - Springfield Women's Club, Springfield, Mass.: publications, 1884-1889, [see also Books on Shelf] (Box 1, Folder 9)
  - Sunderland Woman's Club, Sunderland, Mass.: publications, 1905/1906 (Box 1)
  - Thursday Club, Westborough, Mass.: publications, 1907/1908 (Box 2, Folder 1)
  - Thursday Morning Club, Great Barrington, Mass.: publications, 1901/1902 (Box 2)
  - Tuesday Afternoon Club, Easthampton, Mass.: publications, 1995 (Box 2)
  - Upland Women's Club, Upland, CA: clippings, photographs, manuscripts, correspondence, 1926-50 (Box 2)
  - Waltham Woman's Club, Waltham, Mass.: publications, 1908-1909 (Box 2, Folder 2)
  - Wellesley Hills Woman's Club, Wellesley Hills, Mass.: Program, 1910-11 (Box 2)
  - West Concord Woman's Club, Concord Junction, Mass.: Year Book, 1910-11 (Box 2)
  - Whitman Woman's Club, Whitman, Mass.: publications, 1909-11 (Box 2)
  - Wisconsin, Woman's Club of, Milwaukee, Wis.: Calendar, 1909-10 (Box 2)
  - Woburn Woman's Club, Woburn, Mass.: Year Book, 1907-08 (Box 2, Folder 3)
  - Woman's Baptist Social Union, Boston, Mass.: Gentlemen's Night, 1904 (Box 2)
  - Woman's Congressional Club: magazine 1909 (Box 2)
  - Women's City Club of Boston, [see separate folder] (Box 2)
  - Women's City Club of New York: goals, 1983 (Box 2)
  - Women's ERA Club of Boston (Josephine St. Pierre Ruffin): clippings, 1842-1924 (Box 2)
  - Woman's Literary Club, Dayton, Ohio: publications, 1902-03 (Box 2)
  - Woman's Literary Union, Androscoggin County, Maine: publications, 1909-10 (Box 2)
  - Woman's National Democratic Club, Washington, D.C., 1950, 1951 (By-Laws) (Box 2, Folder 4)
  - Woman's National Farm and Garden Assoc., New York Division, By Laws, 1948 (Box 2)
  - Worcester Woman's Club, Worcester, Mass.: Year Book, 1895/1896, 1909-10 (Box 2)
  - Women's City Club of Boston: book, pamphlets, 1926-30 (Box 2, Folder 5)
  - Yearbook of Women's Clubhouses. Published by the Woman's Journal, 1929-30 (Box 2, Folder 6)
  - General (Box 2, Folder 7)
    - Winslow, Helen M. Literature via the Woman's Club, The Critic, March 1904 (Box 2)
    - Literary Club Women, The Critic, April 1904 (Box 2)
    - The Story of the Woman's Club Movement, New England Magazine, July 1908 (Box 2)
- BOOKS ON SHELF
  - The Mother of Clubs: Caroline M. Seymour Severance, An Estimate and An Appreciation, edited by Ella Giles Ruddy 1906
  - Reminiscences of the Springfield Woman's Club, 1884-1924 by Carrie Niles Whitcomb